A Guide to the Business Records of Firms Located in Albemarle County, Va., 1818-1902
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Business Records of Firms Located in Albemarle County, Va. 1819-1902
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
38-4
46 volumes.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift, Albemarle County Courthouse, 1931.
Scope and Content
A miscellaneous collection of accounts kept in Albemarle County, so far as they can be placed, or in Nelson County, most of them dating from about 1865-1875, with a small number dated earlier and even fewer of later date. The largest group consists of ten lawyer's fee books (1826-1885), one perhaps kept by Ira Garrett and several by John B. Spiece of Afton, Nelson County. Other legal accounts are two from Albemarle County Court (1841-1859), records of sales of slaves and what are perhaps the sheriff's accounts. There are five volumes of accounts (1867-1871) of The Chronicle, a Charlottesville newspaper; three ledgers of the Virginia Loan and Trust Co. (1866-1871); two ledgers of the Albemarle Insurance Co. (1856-1875). Also, two cash books of several postmasters at the University of Virginia (1879-1889), and a register of freight way bills (1866-1869) from Mechum's River Depot and Blair Park. Several merchants of Free Union are represented: James Wayland or James Wayland Wood by three ledgers (1856-1870).
Unidentified merchants of Scottsville kept two ledgers (1821-1832), and there are five ledgers (1822-1874) of unidentified merchants, all probably of Charlottesville. Identified accounts include those of Harris and Taylor (two ledgers 1859-1860), who operated a smithy and foundry; Wertenbaker and Genty, tailors, whose ledger (1861-1863) has the peculiarity of entries in code, probably prices; Marcus W. Haskins, grocer, a ledger for 1870; Seamands and Marshall or Seamands and Co., dealers in grain and lumber, ledger for 1880-1881; R. and J.D Moon, ledger for 1821-1832; the account book for a miller, perhaps one named Mundy, at Millington in Albemarle County. Also accounts of Belmont and Dawson Farms (two ledgers 1869-1899) kept by W.J. Ficklen; and an account of wages paid and miscellaneous expenditures (1869-1902) not identified. A number of loose papers, perhaps as many as a couple of hundred, including letters, promissory notes, and others, laid in some of the ledgers, and probably related to a person who kept the ledgers. In some instances, ledgers in this group are related to ledgers in 38-3.
Contents List
- Register of freight way bills, out, Mechum's River Depot with a few from Blair Park, apparently kept by Jas. Y. Good 1866-1869 (Volume [1])
- Account book and miscellaneous papers 1857-1886 (Volume [2])
  Grocer's account book, 1870, perhaps of M.W. Haskins; miscellaneous papers 1857-1886, including many promissory notes to Marcus W. Haskins, and application of Daniel J. Pruvis for aid to citizens of Virginia wounded in the late war.
- Modern Atlas [1883], 1841-1844, 1889 (Volume [3])
  laid in: Documents, Albemarle County Court, 1841-1844, records of slave sales, and 1889 miscellaneous accounts.
- Merchant ledger, [Charlottesville?] 1870-1872 (Volume [4])
- Account book, wages paid, and other disburments 1896-1902 (Volume [5])
- Account book of Seamands and Marshall 1880-1881 (Volume [6])
  Seamands and Co. dealers in lumber and grain[?]. Evidently Albemarle or Charlottesville.
- Subscription accounts, The Chronicle, Charlottesville 1865-1870 (Volume [7])
- Day book for Blacksmith Shop and Foundry, Harris and Taylor; notably Albemarle 1859-1860 (Volume [8])
- Ledger, The Chronicle, Charlottesville 1867-1870 (Volume [9])
- Day book, general accounts and law account, Albemarle Co. 1877-1885 (Volume [10])
- Account book of Ira Garrett[?] Legal fees, board, wages, etc. 1826-1863 (Volume [11])
- Free Union, Luther M. Dunn[?], clothing, cloth, whisky, coffee, etc. 1867-1868 (Volume [12])
- Day book #7 1869-1876 (Volume [13])
  Albemarle County, a farmer's[?], 18-(?), 188(?). John B. Spiece, Nelson County, legal papers etc., all loose
- Account book 1861-1863, 1867-1871 (Volume [14])
  Wertenbaker and Gentry, clothiers and tailors, Charlottesville, with six loose items 1867-1871, reference debts of the firm. Accounts book is unusual, with prices, presumably, in a code or cipher.
- Account book 1857-1864, 1860-1871 (Volume [15])
  a miller,_______Munday? Loose pieces 1860-1871. Perhaps kept at Millington, Albemarle County.
- Ledger 1823-1870 (Volume [16])
  Loose papers laid in; possibly belonged to John B. Spiece.
- Account book, perhaps an Albemarle lawyer's 1848-1879 (Volume [17])
- Ledger B, Merchant [William Morris?] 1820-1830 (Volume [18])
- Ledger A, [Richard Moore] 1822-1827 (Volume [19])
- Virginia Loan and Trust Co., Charlottesville, ledger, credits "Scratcher of Credits" 1866-1871 (Volume [20])
- Journal A, Richard Moore, general merchandise[?], Scottsville, Va. 1822-1828 (Volume [21])
- Virginia Loan and Trust Co., Charlottesville, "Debit Scratcher" 1866-1871 (Volume [22])
- Ledger, R. and J.D. Moon 1821-1832 (Volume [23])
- R. and J.D. Moon, Journal A, Accounts, rates of general merchandise, Scottsville, Va. 1821-1832 (Volume [24])
- Virginia Loan and Trust Co., Charlottesville, "Individual ledger" 1866-1871 (Volume [25])
- Lawyer's ledger 1861-1889, 1851-1891 (Volume [26])
  perhaps that of John B. Spiece, attorney of Afton, Nelson County, Va. Loose papers, legal, laid in 1851-1891, 8 pieces, John B. Spiece associate.
- Merchant's ledger, Free Union, general merchandise, perhaps that of James Wayland 1868-1870 (Volume [27])
- Account book of Belmont and Dawson Farms; kept by W.J. Ficklen, Charlottesville[?] 1885-1899 (Volume [28])
- Cash book of A. Pendleton Bibb, postmaster, University of Virginia 1885-1889 (Volume [29])
- Lawyer's day book #7, probably from Nelson County 1855-1880 (Volume [30])
- Lawyer's account book, kept by John B. Spiece, Afton, Nelson County[?] 1840-1876 (Volume [31])
- Cash book of Postmaster, University of Virginia, kept by John H. Bibb, R.H. Fife, and A.P. Bibb 1879-1885 (Volume [32])
- Charlottesville ledger, The Chronicle, Taylor & Foster., Prop. 1870-1871 (Volume [33])
- Merchant ledger [Charlottesville?] 1872-1874 (Volume [34])
- Merchant's cash account, Charlottesville 1873 (Volume [35])
- Wayland & Thompson merchant ledger, Free Union, Va. 1867-1870 (Volume [36])
- Lawyer's Ledger, Charlottesville 1869-1871 (Volume [37])
  Includes advertising rates for The Chronicle on both covers.
- Lawyer's fee book 1851-1869 (Volume [38])
  evidently kept in Charlottesville, though inscribed "Preston Bowling, Landersville, Lawrence County, Ala."
- J.W. & and Brother Journal 1856-1861 (Volume [39])
  Possibly James Wayland, Free Union, Va., or John Shuff, Port Republic, Va.
- Albemarle Insurance Co.? Bank book, record of notes for Collection. Charlottesville/Albemarle 1872-1875 (Volume [40])
- Lawyer's fee book, Charlottesville 1842-1850 (Volume [41])
- Register of dividends, Albemarle Insurance Co. 1855-1875 (Volume [42])
- Albemarle County day book 1848-1859 (Volume [43])
- Merchant's ledger, Harris and Taylor, Charlottesville 1859-1860 (Volume [44])
  22 receipts 1859-1860 laid in
- Merchant's ledger, Free Union, probably by James Wayland 1856-1860 (Volume [45])
- Ledger of Charlottesville Chronicle, Taylor and Foster, proprietors 1868-1870 (Volume [46])